A Guide to the James Branch Cabell Papers, 1860s-1960s
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
- Series I--Correspondence 1860s-1960s
  - Westlake, Neda M. 1960 (Box-folder 3.70)
  - Whitty, J.H. 1927 (Box-folder 3.70)
  - Wilgers, E.D. 1921 (Box-folder 3.70)
  - Williams, Blanche Colton 1920-1927 (Box-folder 3.70)
  - Wylie, Elinor 1925 (Box-folder 3.70)
  - Personalized Christmas cards from James Branch Cabell and family (Box-folder 3a.70a)
  - Christmas cards sent to James Branch Cabell and Family (Box-folder 3a.70b)
- Series II--Manuscripts
  Manuscripts of various Cabell writings, many heavily edited in Cabell's handwriting, are contained in these folders. Most of the material has Duke numbers written in pencil on it. Materials include story ideas, notes, early drafts, drawings, school work, essays, poems, and prefaces. Folders 72-76 are labeled with Duke numbers. See also Series IX.
  - Manuscripts of various Cabell writings (Box-folder 4.71)
  - Manuscripts: D139-478 (Box-folder 4.72)
  - Manuscripts: D 479-499 (Box-folder 4.73)
  - Manuscripts: D500-501 (Box-folder 4.74)
  - Manuscripts: D502-518 (Box-folder 4.75)
  - Manuscripts: D848-2323 (Box-folder 4.76)
- Series III--Ephemera, printed material, illustrations, newspaper clippings, etc.
  Much of the material in this series was taken from the books in Cabell's library. It includes printed material, newspaper clippings, illustrations, and other ephemeral.
  - Six copies of an acrostic written by Branch Cabell 1938 (Box-folder 5.77)
    In Goudy Text celebrating the 35th anniversary of The Village Press
  - Newman, Francis-Dust Jacket for Francis Newman (Box-folder 5.78)
  - Letters, preface by Cabell (Box-folder 5.78)
  - Dust jacket for JBC's The Witch Woman 1948 (Box-folder 5.79)
  - Pamphlets, offprints, etc. in Cabell's library (Box-folder 5.80)
  - Various illustrations, drawings, book jackets, bookplates, cards, etc. (Box-folder 5.81)
    Taken from books in Cabell's library.
  - Illustrations and various advertisements for The Eagles's Shadow (Box-folder 5.81a)
  - Rockbridge Alum Springs, Mountain Lake and Dumbarton brochures (Box-folder 5.82)
  - Early versions of map of Poictesme (Box-folder 5.83)
  - First drawing of the Kalki design by JBC (Box-folder 5.83a)
  - Newspaper clippings of various writers (Box-folder 5.84)
  - Our Lady of the Cenacle membership certificate 1958 (Box-folder 5.85)
  - Pamphlets 1932, 1933, 1938, 1953, 1965 (Box-folder 5.86)
  - Photocopied newspaper articles found in books in Cabell's Library (Box-folder 5.87)
  - Printed material: publication notices, invitations, advertisements etc. (Box-folder 6.88)
  - Printed material: publication notices, invitations, advertisements etc. (Box-folder 6.89)
  - Printed Material: Publication notices, advertisements and illustrations (Box-folder 6.89a)
  - Publisher agreements and copyrights 1907-1938 (Box-folder 6.90)
  - American Spectator stock certificate (Box-folder 6.90a)
  - Statements of sales 1930, 1937, 1943 (Box-folder 6.91)
  - Newspaper clippings--articles (Box-folder 6.91a)
  - Joseph Hergesheimer letter to Cabell with article about JBC 1927 (Box-folder 7.91b)
  - The Reviewer, Endorsements (Box-folder 7.91c)
  - Aliester Crowley letter to Cabell with Songs for Italy (Box-folder 7.91d)
  - Cape Henry Day Program, with phrase composed by Cabell 1957 (Box-folder 7.91e)
  - Telegram to Cabell regarding Jurgen; Letter from Lawyer about acquittal (Box-folder 7.91f)
  - Summons delivered to Guy Holt in Jurgen case (Box-folder 7.91g)
  - Jack Woodford's A Break for Poictesme in the New York Magazine Program 1931 (Box-folder 7.91h)
  - Various advertisements for Cabell books (Box-folder 91i)
  - Ballad of Brobdinnag by Vincent Starrett (Box-folder 7.91j)
  - Virginia and U.S. political convention ephemeral late 19th century (Box-folder 7.91L)
  - Sheet music for Canzonet, a song by Reginald C. Robbins and James Branch Cabell 1934 (Box-folder 7.91m)
  - The United States in Literature textbook, containing a Cabell reference (Box-folder 7.91n)
  - Cumulative Index-Works of James Branch Cabell (A-Jol) by John M. Campbell, Jr. and Emmett Peter, Jr. 1900-1930, 1930-1955 (Box-folder 7.91p)
  - Cumulative Index-Works of James Branch Cabell (Jon-Z) by John M. Campbell, Jr. and Emmett Peter, Jr. 1900-1930, 1930-1955 (Box-folder 7.91q)
  - Cabell: A Reconsideration-Edward Wagenknecht 1946 (Box-folder 7.91r)
  - The Later Romantics-Edward Wagenknetch 1945 (Box-folder 7.91r)
  - James Branch Cabell: The Anatomy of Romanticism-Edward Wagenknetch 1945 (Box-folder 7.91r)
  - Ellen Glasgow Triumph and Despair-Edward Wagenknetch 1945 (Box-folder 7.91s)
  - Poems by David Kemple Eichler (Box-folder 7.91s)
  - Poems by Harlan Umansky (Box-folder 7.91T)
  - Rothman, Julius Lawrence, James Branch Cabell, Satirist (Box-folder 7.91u)
  - Schmidt, Otto-journal article inscribed by Schmidt to Cabell (Box-folder 7.91v)
  - Robert M. McBride and Co. published booklist 1923-1943 (Box-folder 7.91w)
  - The Society of the Cincinnati in the State of Virginia-Minutes 1956 (Box-folder 7.91x)
  - Misc. material -In Memoriam, Alice M. Tyler, by James Branch Cabell May 15, 1913 (Box-folder 7.91y)
- Series IV--Cabell Society 1963-1971
  Includes Papers of the Cabell Society, correspondence between its founders, a collection of correspondence between Cabell and Nelson Bond, Cabell and Frederick Eddy.
  - Bond, Nelson: galley proof--Thirty-first of February 1949 (Box-folder 8.92)
  - Bond-Rothman correspondence 1967-1971 (Box-folder 8.93)
  - Bond-Cabell Collection, includes correspondence and part of a manuscript of a bibliography of Cabell (Box-folder 8.93a)
  - Cabell Society general information (Box-folder 8.94)
  - Fox, Lawrence (Larry): correspondence 1964-1967 (Box-folder 8.95)
  - Fox, Lawrence (Larry): miscellaneous 1963-1965 (Box-folder 8.96)
  - Rothman-Fox correspondence 1967-1968 (Box-folder 8.97)
  - Eddy, Frederick-Galley proof of Figures of Earth and letters to Eddy (Box-folder 8.97a)
  - Material removed from Fox, Applebaum and Bond copies of books by JBC (Box-folder 8.97b)
- Series V--Between Friends
  Materials concerning Between Friends: Letters of James Branch Cabell and Others edited by Padraic Colum and Margaret Freeman Cabell, published in 1962.
  - Copies of letters considered for inclusion #1 (Box-folder 9.98)
  - Copies of letters considered for inclusion #2 (Box-folder 9.99)
  - Copies of letters and text of Chapter 10 (Box-folder 9.100)
  - Proofs (Box-folder 9.101)
- Series VI--Criticisms of Cabell's work
  The majority of these criticisms of Cabell and his work were copied from various periodicals (many from microfilm) for Jean Maurice Duke's James Branch Cabell: A Reference Guide published in 1979. Others have been collected by Special Collections & Archives.
  - Criticisms 1904-1922 (Box-folder 10.107-10.120)
  - Criticisms 1923-1933 (Box-folder 10.121-10.131)
  - Criticisms 1934-1977 (Box-folder 10.132-10.162)
- Series VII--Periodicals (essays, reviews and fiction by Cabell)
  Most of the material contained in this series is located in twenty-two bound volumes containing magazines where many of Cabell's book reviews, essays, short stories and other fiction originally appeared before they were later revised into book form. Each volume is named for a published Cabell book and contains the original magazine contribution. There are also two boxes of non-bound journals.
  - A Note as to Sinclair Lewis- American Mercury, August 1930, oversize (Box-folder 13.163)
  - Autobiographic Summary- Trend Jan. 7, 1922, oversize (Box-folder 13.164)
  - Between Worlds- American Mercury-Sept. 1926, oversize (Box-folder 13.165)
  - The Comedies of William Congreve- International-June 1929, oversize (Box-folder 13.166)
  - The Eagles's Shadow- Saturday Evening Post Oct. 1, 1904, oversize (Box-folder 13.167)
  - Ellen Glasgow-Book-of-the-Month Club News-August 1935, oversize (2 copies) (Box-folder 14.168)
  - Kindly Omit Flowers- American Mercury-June 1929, oversize (Box-folder 14.169)
  - Lady into Facts-photocopy- The Saturday Review February 18, 1933, oversize (Box-folder 14.170)
  - Messer Marco Polo: A Very Magically Beautiful Book- The Centurion-June 1922, oversize (Box-folder 14.171)
  - Of Messer Marco Polo, Sixteen Years Later- Reading and Collecting-October 1937, oversize (Box-folder 14.172)
  - Near a Flag-American Mercury-July 1931, oversize (Box-folder 14.173)
  - Once More the Immortals- American Mercury-January 1924, oversize (Box-folder 14.174)
  - Prince Dribbles Burial- Red Book-May 1911, oversize (Box-folder 14.175)
  - They Buried Me Alive- American Mercury-December 1951, oversize (2 copies) (Box-folder 14.176)
  - William and Mary College Quarterly, oversize (Box-folder 14.177)
  - American Spectator Vol. 1 no. 1-12, Vol. 2 no. 13-21, Vol.2 no. 22-28 (Box-folder 13.178)
  - Blue Bound Volumes
    Twenty-two bound volumes containing magazines where many of Bell's book reviews, essays, short stories and other fiction originally appeared before they were later revised into book form. Each blue bound volume is titled after a Bell book and contains the original magazine contribution.
    - The Second Chance- Harper's Monthly-October 1909
    - Balthazor's Daughter- Smart Set-May 1913
    - Belhs Cavaliers- Lippincott's Magazine-June 1915
    - Judiths's Creed- Lippincott's Magazine-July 1915
    - A Brown Woman- Lippincott's Magazine-August 1915
    - Pro Honoria- McBride's Magazine-Sept. 1915
    - The Irresistible Ogle- McBride's Magazine-October 1915
    - The Fox Brush- Harper's Monthly-August 1905
    - The Sestina- Harper's Monthly-January 1906
    - The Housewife- Harper's Monthly-August 1906
    - The Tension- Harper's Monthly-December 1906
    - The Navarrese- Harper's Monthly-September 1907
    - The Rat-Trap- Harper's Monthly-December 1907
    - The Choices- Harper's Monthly-March 1908
    - The Scabbard- Harper's Monthly-April 1909
    - The Satraps- Harper's Monthly-April 1909
    - Afternoon in Arden- Smart Set-July 1902
    - As the Coming of Dawn- Smart Set-September 1902
    - An Incarnation of Helen- Smart Set-October 1902
    - The Story of Stella- Smart Set-August 1903
    - Old Capulet's Daughter- Smart Set-September 1903
    - The Ultimate Master- Harper's Monthly-November 1908
    - The Soul of Mervisaunt- Harper's Monthly-April 1911
    - The Feathers of Olrun- Century Magazine-December 1919
    - The Designs of Miramen- Century Magazine-August 1920
    - The Image of Sesphra- Romance-October 1920
    - The Hour of Freydis- McClure's Magazine-May 1920
    - The Head of Misery- McClure's Magazine-July 1920
    - The Hair of Melicent- McClure's Magazine-September 1920
    - As Played Before His Highness- Smart Set-March 1902
    - In the Summer of Saint Martin- Smart Set-August 1902
    - Heart of Gold- Smart Set-April 1905
    - Simon's Hour- Ainslee's Magazine-April 1905
    - Actors All- Appletons-May 1906
    - In the Second April- Harper's Monthly-April, May 1907
    - The Rhyme to Porringer- Collier's Weekly April 15, 1907
    - Balthazar's Daughter- Smart Set-July 1921
    - An Amateur Ghost- Argosy-February 1902
    - Some Ladies and Jurgen- Smart Set-July 1918
    - To Ananias, Citizen of Jerusalem- Direction-Autumn Issue 1934
    - Books I Have Never Read- The Nation November 8, 1933
    - His Excellency, George Washington- American Spectator-August 1934
    - The Pompadour- American Spectator-September 1934
    - Love Letters of Falstaff- Harper's Monthly-March 1902
    - In Ursula's Garden- Harper's Monthly-May 1903
    - The Conspiracy of Arnaye- Harper's Monthly-June 1903
    - The Castle of Content- Harper's Monthly-August 1903
    - The Story of Adhelmer- Harper's Monthly-April 1904
    - In Necessity's Motor- Harper's Monthly-October 1904
    - Sweet Adelais- Harper's Monthly-October 1905
    - The Line of Love Vol. III
    - The Wedding Jest- Century Magazine-September 1919
    - Porcelain Cups- Century Magazine-November 1919
    - The Shadowy Past- Smart Set-January 1903
    - The Husbands' Comedy- Smart Set-June 1903
    - The Awakening- Smart Set-February 1904
    - A Fordyce of Westbrook- Red Book-July 1909
    - His Relics- Ainslee's Magazine-November 1909
    - Above Paradise- American Mercury-February 1925
    - The Candid Footprint- Century Magazine-May 1922
    - The Mathematics of Gonfal- Century Magazine-August 1925
    - What Saraide Wanted- Red Book-November 1925
    - In the Sylan's House- Red Book-March 1926
    - Cloth at Portasa- Red Book-May 1926
    - A Little More About Eve- American Mercury-January 1929
    - Confusions of the Golden Travel- Bookman-September 1927
    - Ruth Universal- Bookman-February 1933
    - Breast of the Nymph- Bookman-March 1933
    - For Rhadamanthus, Smiling- Bookman-January 1933
    - Study in Sincerity- American Spectator-January 1933
    - Prose of a Pall Bearer- American Spectator-December 1932
    - Art, Beauty and Balderdash Saturday Review of Literature-June 1932
    - Common Places- American Spectator-February 1933
    - The Genteel Tradition in Sex- American Spectator-November 1932
    - Mirror and Pigeons- Bookman-December 1932
    - In Respect to Jeseph Hergeshimer- Bookman-November/December 1919
    - It is of Linda- Bookman-January 1920
    - The Thin Queen of Elfame- Century Magazine-December 1922
    - Once More, The Immortals- American Mercury-January 1924
    - Roque's March: To a Flemish Air- Dial February 22, 1919
    - Beauty and Wizardry- The Nation November 2, 1921
    - A Note on Alcoves- New Republic April 12, 1922
    - Portrait of the Artist: Full Length- Intrn. Book Review-November 1923
    - The Delta of Radegonade- Vanity Fair-June 1921
    - Romantics About Them- Literary Review-N.Y. Eve. Post March 1, 1921
    - Before Aesred- Virginia Quarterly Review-October 1931
    - Near a Flag- American Mercury-July 1931
    - Kindly Omit Flowers- The American Mercury-June 1929
    - Between Worlds- The American Mercury-September 1926
    - Bound edition of Harper's Monthly-Vol. 102-contains In Ursula's Garden 1903
    - Bound edition of Harper's Monthly-Vol. 4-Contains Love Letters of Flastaff 1902
- Series VIII--Dramatic and musical interpretations of Cabell's work
  - Jurgen, A Comedy of Justice by James Branch Cabell and Charlton Andrews play 1922 (Box-folder 15.179)
  - The Irresistible Ogle-A One-Act Play by A. Eugene Dieaderick 1923 (Box-folder 15.180)
  - The Rivet in Grandfather's Neck, A Comedy a screenplay by Sidney Howard and Barrett Clark 1920 (Box-folder 15.181)
  - Rendezvous A Romantic Drama in One Act a play by Knight 1920s (Box-folder 15.182)
  - A Brown Woman a play by Peter Ridgeway 1930 (Box-folder 15.183)
  - Light O'Love-A Play in One Act by Lucile Rutland 1909 (Box-folder 15.184)
  - The Fox-Brush-A Play in One Act by Lucile Rutland 1909 (Box-folder 15.185)
  - Manual's Adventure a play by Katherine J. Townsend 1920s (Box-folder 15.186)
  - The Cream of the Jest-Radio Play 1947 (Box-folder 15.187)
  - Jurgen, symphonic poem by Deems Taylor, program notes (Box-folder 15.188)
  - Jurgen, satirical movie treatment 1927 (Box-folder 15.189)
  - Various advertisements, photos and other memorabilia of Cabell theatre productions 15.190
  - Bayes Theatre program with Simon's Hour written by Cabell performed in Conneticut 1926 (Box-folder 15.191)
  - Stadium Concerts Review program, Jurgen production 1930 (Box-folder 15.192)
- Series IX--Scrapbooks, notebooks and oversized items
  - Scrapbook One 1902-1905, oversize, 51 sheet bound volume (Box 16)
    A 51 sheet (8 1/2 x 10 1/2) bound volume of material about Cabell. Contains many newspaper and magazine articles by and about Cabell, most regarding his published fiction and book reviews at this time. They are pasted in the volume and many are identified and dated. Most of the dates are 1902-1905. It also contains a letter to Cabell from an editor at Smart Set, dated Sept. 30, 1902, suggesting Cabell write them a novelette.
    It also has a 15 page (7 1/2 x 10 1/2) folder in which several newspaper advertisements of The Eagle's Shadow are pasted. All are dated 1904.
  - Scrapbook Two, oversize, 83 sheet bound volume (Box 16)
    The first 35 sheets contain newspaper clippings of articles written by Cabell for the Richmond News during the first few years of the century.
    The next 25 sheets are newspaper clippings about Cabell and his family, dated around 1910. These pages also include genealogical articles written by Cabell and others.
    The remaining sheets contain letters to Cabell regarding genealogy dating form 1909 to 1919; obituaries and articles about John R. Branch, newspaper society columns; a New York Herald style pamphlet; a 1895 Navy Department letter to Cabell regarding a post for him in the Navel Academy; a 1906 letter from the U.S. State Department regarding an appointment for Cabell as Secretary of Legation in Athens, Greece or in South America and a 1906 letter from the White House regretting Cabell's decision not to accept the position in the State Department. There are also programs of plays performed in 1896 by the Virginia Comedians. Cabell was in five of them.
    On the verso of p. 82 and recto of p. 83 is pasted a printed article entitled "That Opera Bouffe Court Martial." It describes a court martial at the U.S. Naval Academy where midshipman James Robinson Branch, Jr. died after a boxing match with another student named Meriwether. Branch was the son of James R. Branch, James Branch Cabell's uncle.
  - Scrapbook Three 1911-1917, oversize, bound volume of 112 sheets (Box 17)
    This is a bound volume of 112 sheets (8 1/2 x 10 1/2) containing a large amount of many kinds of material concerning Cabell and his writings.
    There are almost 100 letters to him. Many are from publishers to whom he had sent, or offered to send, a manuscript. In some of these the publishers offered to read his book. In others they gave their opinions of it and their decision on publishing. Most of these say that while they appreciated the quality of his work they cannot publish it, usually because they do not think it would be profitable. There are a few letters asking him to submit material to them. Many others are from individuals who have read something by or about him. Most of this material is dated from 1911-1917.
    There are also more than 100 newspaper and magazine clippings about him, his family and his books. Some are advertisements, some are reviews. They come from all over the country and nearly all are dated and have the name of the source. It appears that a clipping service must have supplied many of them. There are also a few photographs of Cabell.
  - Notebook One, oversize, notebook with 200 numbered pages (Box 18)
    Bound note book with 200 numbered pages. Pages 3-34 are missing. The remaining pages have a variety of material in Cabell's hand, including lists of stories written year by year, where published, amount paid him, books published, copies received, number sold, royalties, etc. Also, poems; many pages of genealogical materials on his family; wills of family members; notes on his books, including to whom submitted and results; other material on his writing, such as Suppressed Foreword to the Cords of Vanity: rough draft.
  - Notebook Two, oversize, Bound note book with 144 numbered pages (Box 18)
    Bound note book with 144 numbered pages. First page has a note written and signed by Cabell stating: Verses, etc., as written 1896-1898. Selected, revised, and copied in this book 1898-1899. James Branch Cabell.
  - Folder 1 (Box-folder 18.1)
    Unbound material which was found in notebook two.
    Most of this material concerns The Majors and Their Marriages (1915). Some is typed, some printed. Includes genealogical notes, lists, etc. and correspondence concerning these families. Includes a little material on the Cabells.
  - Folder 2 (Box-folder 18.2)
    This has Cabell materials inserted in the covers of two typewriter paper covers.
    In the first typewriter paper cover material includes two typewritten Cabell manuscripts of poems, "The Ways of Women." There are some textual differences and some pencil changes (9 & 7 pages). There is also a two-page typewritten manuscript of Cabell's reminiscences written when he was 77. Has a few pencil corrections and additions. A one page Cabell typewritten manuscript entitled Frail Rymes, with Studrdy Morals.
    In the second typewriter paper cover material includes two copies of a four page list of manuscripts, etc. of his writings. A 15 page typewritten manuscript entitled "Composition book No. 341." An eight page typewritten manuscript entitled "List of Horses in the collection." A four page typewritten manuscript entitled "Unpublished Matter." and a one page typewritten list of some of his books, some including the color of binds, etc.
  - Notebook Three, oversize, spring back notebook with about 60 leaves (Box 18)
    They contain photographic copies of Cabell manuscripts, both poetry and prose. Some are identified.
  - Notebook Four, oversize, spring back notebook (Box 19)
    A spring back notebook with more than 100 typewritten pages containing information on the ancestry of Priscilla Bradley (Mrs. James Branch Cabell). Includes genealogical notes, abstracts from books and magazines, correspondence, etc. Some of the items are dated after the publication of the genealogy of her family, The Majors and Their Marriages (1915). One folder includes an essay written by Cabell when he was 77 years old, discussing his lack of literary recognition and awards.
  - Notebook Five, oversize, spring back notebook (Box 19)
    A spring back notebook with about 150 pages, mostly typewritten, about the Cabell family genealogy. The material was collected over many years and was compiled and supplied by many people.
    Inserted inside the front cover was more material on the Cabell family. There are about 40 pages, some typewritten, and some newspaper clippings and other items. This material is now is a folder.
  - Cabell Biblio, oversize (Box 20)
    A bound volume containing a 37 page check list of Cabell's books and other material held by ULS' Special Collections & Archives made by Daniel E. Jones in 1973.
    A bound volume with about 30 pages of bibliographic notes on Cabell and his writings, described as a supplement to I.R. Brussel's A Bibliography of the Writings of James Branch Cabell, 1932.
    A folder contains copies of nine Cabell letters to Desmond Tarrant, 1953-1959, and one letter to Tarrant from Margaret Freeman Cabell, 1964. They are concerned with Tarrant's proposed book on Cabell, later published as James Branch Cabell: The Dream and the Reality, 1967. Also contains copies of two letters Cabell wrote to Guy Holt, 1917 and 1918.
    The material in a small box labelled Cabelliana was transferred to Series III. A list of the few items in that box has been left in it.
  - Cabell Letters, oversize (Box 21)
    Contains the letters labelled Apfelbaum-Cabell Letters, which include Cabell letters to the editor of The Literary Review, 22 letters to Mourice Speiser, one letter from Herbert Speiser to Robert McBride & Co., and an answer to it from McBride.
    A 14 page photocopied list of Cabell books taken from The National Union Catalog Pre-1956 Imprints
    23 pages of genealogical oversized photocopied notes on the Branch family. Material includes photocopies of family Bibles, lists of marriages and births with dates up until 1981.
  - Miscellaneous Oversize Material, oversize (Oversize 23.1)
    A 24 x 9 inch poster of Cabell's review of The Adventures of the Black Girl in her search for God by Bernard Shaw. A book review reprinted from the New York Herald Tribune Books Section, Sunday, February 26, 1933.
    Painting of Family Tree by Cabell
    Miscellaneous Drawings and Advertisements